Guide to the Esther Tappert Mortensen Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Esther Tappert Mortensen Papers
1903-1972
RG 21
Yale University Divinity School Library
3
(8 boxes)
The papers provide documentation of a missionary who served in varied roles in China during the turbulent period of 1929 to 1953. The later letters from Shanghai provide information about the situation in the city after the Communist takeover. Esther Tappert taught English at Ginling College, a mission-sponsored women's college in Nanking, China from 1929 to 1931 and 1933 to1937. From 1937 to 1939 she taught English at Chungking University, a Chinese government university. She returned to the U.S. in 1940 and completed her doctorate at Yale. In 1945 she returned to China, married Ralph Mortensen and lived in Shanghai until January, 1953.
Mortensen, Esther Tappert
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Ralph Mortensen
Biographical / Historical
Arriving in China as a single woman, thirty years of age, Esther Tappert taught English at Ginling College, a Christian women's college in Nanking, for three years before returning to the United States. Esther described her role at Ginling as "trying to make good women who can read and write English and save China."
Returning to Ginling in 1933 after receiving an M.A. in Education from Yale, Esther continued teaching English there until the summer of 1937. When the Japanese invasion of Nanking prevented her return from a vacation excursion to western China, she spent the next two academic years teaching English at Chungking University, a Chinese provincial government university. This proved to be a positive and liberating experience for Esther. The only Westerner on the faculty at Chungking University, she felt useful and respected. Reflecting during this period on her years at Ginling, Esther wrote to her family: "no wonder I am death on women's institutions with their petty spites and trivial concerns..."
After leaving Chungking in 1940 to return to the United States, Esther became engaged to Ralph Mortensen, a widowed Lutheran missionary who was working for the American Bible Society in China. She completed work for her doctorate at Yale and sailed for Shanghai in November 1945. Esther was married to Ralph Mortensen in January, 1946 and her primary role for the next several years was that of missionary wife. Following the Communist takeover, the Mortensens were held in Shanghai until January, 1953 because of suspicion regarding Ralph Mortensen's activities.
Scope and Contents
Esther Tappert Mortensen's twenty years in China are well documented in regular and detailed letters to her family. These letters report on Esther's activities, reflections, and emotions in her daily work and recreation. They also document wartime conditions in China and special events such as the visit of Charles and Anne Morrow Lindbergh to the Ginling campus in 1931. Esther's correspondence with colleagues at Ginling shows her to be a strong-minded individual who became increasingly discontent with her status at Ginling. Additional correspondence and documentation of Esther's Ginling years is available in YDSL Record Group No. 11, the Archives of the United Board for Christian Higher Education in Asia.
The letters from the period after Esther's marriage to Ralph Mortensen tend to be more domestic in nature and reflect a more contented frame of mind. These letters from Shanghai do provide valuable information about the situation in the city after the Communist takeover.
Arrangement
I. Family Correspondence, 1929-1953
II. General Correspondence, 1929-1955
III. Writings and Collected Material, 1924-1951
IV. Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1916-1972
Education -- China; Missions -- China; Women -- Education -- China; Educators; Missionaries; Mortensen, Esther Tappert; Mortensen, Ralph; Chungking University; Ginling College (Nanjing, Jiangsu Sheng, China)
- Family Correspondence, 1929-1953; Series I
  - ETM letters home to family, 1929 Aug - 1930 (Box 1, Folder 1-14)
  - ETM letters home to family, 1931 -1933 Nov (Box 2, Folder 15-30)
  - ETM letters home to family, 1933 Nov 24-1936 May 7 (Box 3, Folder 31-49)
  - ETM letters home to family, 1936 May 17-1940 Jun (Box 4, Folder 50-68)
  - ETM letters home to family, 1940 Jul - 1953 Jan (Box 5, Folder 69-82)
  - Mother to ETM, 1929-1931 Jul (Box 2, Folder 83-86)
  - Mother to ETM, 1931 Aug-1940 (Box 6, Folder 87-93)
  - Helen (sister) to ETM, 1929-1938, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 94-96)
  - Other family members, 1903-1937, n.d.6 (Box 6, Folder 97)
- General Correspondence, 1929-1955; Series II
  - Circular letters by ETM, 1930-1934 (Box 6, Folder 98)
  - Circular letters by ETM, 1935-1955 (Box 6, Folder 99)
  - Associated Boards for Christian Higher Education in Asia, 1933, 1938 (Box 6, Folder 100)
  - Bachman, Matilda, 1938-1939 (Box 6, Folder 100)
  - Bates, Miner Searle, 1937-1940 (Box 6, Folder 101)
  - Chen Lan-ying, 1938 (Box 6, Folder 101)
  - Chungking University: administration, faculty, staff, 1939 (Box 6, Folder 101)
  - Cooper, Grady, 1930-1932 (Box 6, Folder 102)
  - Curtis, Catherine, 1929 (Box 6, Folder 103)
  - Djeng Ying-hwan, 1937 (Box 6, Folder 103)
  - Endicott, 1938 (Box 6, Folder 103)
  - Federation of Woman's Boards of Foreign Missions, 1933 (Box 6, Folder 103)
  - Garing, Trudy, 1932 (Box 6, Folder 103)
  - Ginling College Committee, 1929-1933 (Box 7, Folder 104-105)
  - Loram, C.T., 1938 (Box 7, Folder 106)
  - Moffet, Anna, 1938 (Box 7, Folder 106)
  - Moncrieff, 1938 (Box 7, Folder 106)
  - Mortensen, Ralph, 1940, 1944 Jul-Aug (Box 7, Folder 107)
  - Mortensen, Ralph, 1944 Sep-Nov, 1954 (Box 7, Folder 108)
  - Nowlin, 1939 (Box 7, Folder 109)
  - Peck, Willys, 1938 (Box 7, Folder 109)
  - Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A., Board of Foreign Missions, 1929-1933 (Box 7, Folder 109)
  - Priest, Elsie (Treasurer of Ginling College), 1929-1940 (Box 7, Folder 110)
  - Rees, 1938 (Box 7, Folder 110)
  - Reich, Lydia, 1930, 1936 (Box 7, Folder 110)
  - Rosenthal, Oskar, 1940 (Box 7, Folder 111)
  - Smythe, Lewis, 1938 (Box 7, Folder 111)
  - Spicer, Eva, 1938-1940 (Box 7, Folder 111)
  - Sutherland, Catharine, 1931-1938 (Box 7, Folder 112)
  - Thurston, Matilda, 1938-1940 (Box 7, Folder 112)
  - Treudley, Mary, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 112)
  - United Lutheran Church, 1932 (Box 7, Folder 113)
  - Vautrin, Minnie, 1933-1937 (Box 7, Folder 113)
  - Wu Yi-fang, 1937-1939 (Box 7, Folder 113)
  - Yale University, 1932-1933 (Box 7, Folder 114)
  - Regarding business and travel arrangements, 1933-1940, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 115)
- Writings, Collected Material, 1924-1951; Series III
  - Writings of ETM
    - Diary of ETM, 1924-1925 (Box 7, Folder 116)
    - Travel journal of ETM, 1937 Jul-Sep (Box 7, Folder 117)
    - "The China I Know and the China I am to Discover" (Box 7, Folder 118)
    - "Martha on the Mission Field or On Being 'Only a Wife'", n.d. (Box 7, Folder 118)
    - Miscellaneous, 1940, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 119)
  - Writings of others
    - Writings of Miner Searle Bates, 1936-1938 (Box 7, Folder 120)
    - "And Yet - Jesus Christ", by Pearl Buck (Box 7, Folder 121)
    - "Christianity and the Churches", by John Macmurray" (Box 7, Folder 121)
    - "Factors Associated with Success of Chinese Families as Families", by Lewis S.C. Smythe, 1950 (Box 8, Folder 122)
  - Material related to Ginling College
    - Re. Ginling College, c.1937-1944 (Box 8, Folder 123)
  - Other documents
    - "Address to the Commission of Inquiry of the League of Nations", 1932 (Box 8, Folder 124)
    - "Cooperative New Rural Life Program", n.d. (Box 8, Folder 124)
    - Community Church - Shanghai, Resident Membership List, 1950 (Box 8, Folder 124)
    - Document for the Transfer of Administrative Power of the North China Territory of the Salvation Army, 1951 (Box 8, Folder 124)
- Personal Items Memorabilia, 1916-1972; Series IV
  - Documents and memorabilia related to ETM's education and career, 1916-1940 (Box 8, Folder 125)
  - ETM travel documents, cards, Chinese language material (Box 8, Folder 126)
  - Photographs, 1947, 1953, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 127)
  - Material related to Ralph Mortensen, 1946-1972, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 128)
  - Financial records related to life in Shanghai, 1952-1953 (Box 8, Folder 129)